Robert B. August Papers VHP2005/2
CCSU Veterans History Project
Robert B. August Papers
Bulk, 1943-1945
1943-1945, 1988, 2008
VHP2005/2
CCSU Veterans History Project
89.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This Collection details Robert Augusts’ experiences, relationships, travels, and reflections while serving the United States in World War II. The Collection consists of a 70 minute video taped interview performed by Eileen Hurst, photographs, and an unpublished manuscript of war memoirs. The materials provide insight into life on a U.S. landing craft, and the social and cultural aspects of Pacific Islanders during World War II.
August, Robert B., (Robert Burton), 1921 -
Biographical/Historical note
Robert B. August originally enlisted in the Naval Air Corps while a student at Yankton College and washed out in flight training. To qualify for a commission, he completed his degree in three years. In August 1943 he was assigned to Northwestern University in Chicago for three months of midshipman training. After Northwestern, he was trained as a ship's engineering officer for three months at Cornell University. After completion of training at Cornell he was assigned to LSFF 504, a landing ship support vessel at Solomons, MD, as the ship's Engineering Officer. The 504 sailed to San Diego, CA via the Panama Canal and then to Hawaii where it served for six months as an amphibious training ship. It then sailed to Sasebo Harbor, Japan with a stop at the Philippines. While in Japan the ship was the flagship for a command engaged in the transport of military personnel from Korea. The ship returned to San Diego where August commanded the ship, in harbor, prior to his discharge. From San Diego he traveled cross-country by car to Connecticut. On the trip, he attended a commencement at Yankton to get his degree. He then obtained a Law Degree from Georgetown on the GI Bill and has practiced law from 1950 to the date of interview. He has been an active member of VFW post 3272 in Avon (CT) from 1946 to date
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
United States. Navy.; USS LC(FF)-504.; Chicago (Ill.); Hawaii; Interviews; Manuscript; Panama Canal (Panama); Photographs; San Diego (Calif.); Sasebo-shi (Japan); Solomons (Md.); World War, 1939-1945 -- Amphibious operations; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Area; World War, 1939-1945 -- Naval operations; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers
  - RBA and the Navy, December 1988; VHP2005/2.I.1; 31.0 Digital files
  - Interview Synopsis, February 23, 2005; VHP2005/2.I.2
- Series II: Multi-Media
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2005/2.II
    - Photograph of Robert B. August before his enlistment in the United States Navy, circa 1940 - 1942; VHP2005/2.II.1
    - Robert August in naval dress uniform, 1943; VHP2005/2.II.2
    - Lil Olsen on the deck of a ship, circa 1943-1945; VHP2005/2.II.3
    - Young Japanese boy carrying a baby on his back, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.4
    - Two babies on a dirt road, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.5
    - Street scene at Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.6
    - African American G.I. in Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.7
    - Street scene at Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.8
    - Two sailors helping a Japanese woman retrieve water from a well, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.9
    - Young Japanese boy wearing a coat and hat, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.10
    - Group of children, Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.11
    - Japanese Stone mason. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.12
    - Japanese woman driving a bicycle powered cab. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.13
    - Japanese auto powered by an exposed outboard engine, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.14
    - Robert August’s crew posing with a group of Japanese children, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.15
    - Crowded street scene. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.16
    - Smiling seamstress. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.17
    - Street vendor. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.18
    - Street scene of Sasebo, Japan depicting a woman with small children, an enlisted person walking down the street and a Japanese youngster, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.19
    - Robert Miller kneeling with young child and puppy. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.20
    - Landscape scene depicting men amid bricks and lumber, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.21
    - Japanese carts filled with lumber, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.22
    - Rice fields, near Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.23
    - Rice fields at the base of a mountain, Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.24
    - Rice fields in levels with dwellings and mountains in the background. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.25
    - Japanese street vendor selling produce. Nagasaki, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.26
    - Three children playing among rubble. Nagasaki, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.27
    - American sailor amid the rubble of bombed out buildings. Nagasaki, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.28
    - Al Caboni in a kneeling pose. Nagasaki, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.29
    - Robert August in a kneeling pose. Nagasaki, Japan 1945, VHP2005/2.II.30
    - Sacred Heart Church. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.31
    - Parishioners outside Sacred Heart Church. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.32
    - Congregants worshipping inside Sacred Heart Church. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.33
    - Several pairs of shoes at the threshold of a dwelling. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.34
    - American enlisted man making confession to a Japanese Priest at the Sacred Heart Roman Catholic Church. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.35
    - Aerial view of Sasebo Harbor. Sasebo, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.36
    - Approaching American military landing craft, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.37
    - View of an American military Landing craft’s bow, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.38
    - Close-up view of the starboard and bow of an American military Landing craft, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.39
    - Starboard view of a Landing Ship, Tank (LST), 1945; VHP2005/2.II.40
    - Tank Landing Ship (LST) being tied up, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.41
    - Head signalman (foreground) with two other sailors aboard ship, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.42
    - View of ship from the port side, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.43
    - American sailors aboard ship, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.44
    - Robert August's LST-504 crew, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.45
    - Naval officer holding a bull horn, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.46
    - #354 Landing craft docked, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.47
    - Head signalman Milner carrying his duffel and rifle, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.48
    - Decorating the Christmas tree aboard ship. Sasebo Harbor, Japan, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.49
    - Moon (foreground) wearing white sailors cap carrying packages in his pocket and his duffel, Hawaii, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.50
    - Moon and Milner (the Black Gang -- the gang that ran ship's mechanicals), 1945; VHP2005/2.II.51
    - Grand Coulee Dam, Grand Coulee, Washington, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.52
    - Aerial view of Grand Coulee Dam. Grand Coulee, Washington, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.53
    - Robert August with a 1931 Oldsmobile on his way from California to Yanketon, South Dakota, 1945; VHP2005/2.II.54
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2005/2.IIb
    - Oral History Interview, February 23, 2005; VHP2005/2.IIb.1; 1.0 dvd; August, Robert B., (Robert Burton), 1921 -; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2005/2, Box VHP Interview #1)